Hello and welcome to this BC LE session
on AL graph. I am Thaddeus. I am an
engineer working on the team that builds
a lot of this AL tooling. Um, and so
this is one of the newer tools that we
built in the last release. So, let's get
into this. So, what is AL graph? Um, it
is a new tool that's part of the AL
tools package. If you have used AL tools
before, um, you've probably seen that
over the releases we've added more and
more capabilities to it. Uh, and this is
a new one. It is a tool that is focused
around constructing call graphs.
Um, so if you've ever wanted to know,
like, you know, the structure of your
code, like, who is calling who, what are
your external integration points, what
are your dependencies, where are you
calling into certain sensitive
libraries, or what services are you
exposing that other PTEs or other global
apps could take a dependency on,
this tool helps you answer all of those
questions.
It basically allows you to do auditing
of your code base.
So, for example, if you've ever wanted
to know where in your code do you make
HTTP requests, and what are the
different call paths that can reach
there? You know, what actions on your
pages can actually end up uh, issuing a
history request? Or, if you want to do
security auditing, one big one
um, that we're quite focused on is the
non-debuggable to debuggable boundary.
Um, because, you know, you can
inadvertently expose secrets that way.
Um, this tool allows you to catch all of
this uh, sooner, and just basically
answer questions about how your code
base is structured. The query language
is pretty rich, uh, so you can actually
uh,
construct fairly complex queries. So, if
you have your own sensitive objects, for
example, you can say, "Okay, give me all
the callers of this particular object."
Or, "Give me all the different methods
that interact with this specific table,
etc."
And then you have multiple uh, um export
formats that you can export this as
DGML, which is great for humans because,
you know, it's a nice graph
representation,
which is how we think about call graphs.
But, you know, there's also the SARIF
format, you know, if you're interested
in something more flat uh that um agent
can act on easily.
So, let's get into it. Let's get into
the demo and let's see how this works.
The first thing you need to do before
you query your um code is you actually
need to build the meta model. So, this
is a one-time thing. It's basically
building the representation of
the different uh caller-callee
relationships in your app. So, this is
the command. This basically AL graph.
Um
actually, what I should do first is I
should actually show you AL graph
itself. So, give me a second.
And here we go. Let's see AL graph
itself. And there's a whole bunch of
different front like subcommands you can
use uh that allows you to do all sorts
of different things. Um so, I'm going to
use the
extract whole uh method. And this
basically it constructs the meta model.
And you only do this once. So, you
construct the meta model once and then
you run your queries on the meta model.
Um we don't really need to worry about
the internal representation. So, it's a
JSON file. Um doesn't really matter.
Um what is What then becomes interesting
is querying it, right? So, for example,
if I wanted to find out all my callers
to HTTP client, I could run the
following query, right? Uh so, AL graph
export.
Uh and then the graph is the graph that
we produced previously. And then it's,
you know, I want this in DGML format,
exclude all my test files. Um and I want
everything that targets the HTTP client.
So, let's actually run this.
Right? And let's actually view the
output. So, it's this one that we just
generated here.
Um and if we zoom in
Yeah, so this is basically what it is.
If I see all the different gets Well,
there's only one caller to
get and post, but then if we actually
follow this, we can see this has three
callers.
And then this one has its its own
caller, but this one has another caller
further. And so, you can basically trace
the call path. You get the idea, right?
Like this is the tree of the different
caller callee relationships in your
code.
Now,
let's do another interesting query.
Let's do
one that shows the
your non-debuggable to debuggable
boundaries.
And the this query language that all the
different operations you can do this is
all well documented on our um MS Learn
website. So, you don't have to worry
about the exact like, you know,
um format of this query. Just know that
there is a query language you can use.
Um so, this is a very similar thing. So,
you'll notice that I'm using the same
graph that we generated in the first
step. So, that's the idea. You generate
the graph once and then you query it
multiple times.
Okay. Same thing. I want it from all my
non-debuggables and I want to find all
the callees of my non-debuggable
methods. And so, I want to audit them.
Let's run this.
All right. And then if we go
here, this is the one that was
generated. Let's open this.
Right. And so, this is what it looks
like. So, these are the non-debuggable
that it's This one calls into a
platform. Built-in suggestions should be
safe. This one's a bit interesting
because, you know, I've got a
non-debuggable method. It's the one
that's outlined by in red. And it's
calling into a debuggable method. So, we
can actually go and look at the
uh source of this.
All right. And you can see that, you
know, it's a simplified example, but you
can see here that, you know, if there's
a breakpoint on this line, for example,
you can actually read content of text.
All right.
So, even though like the main procedure
is non-debuggable and this is a local
procedure, you're still leaking
information this way. It's a simplified
example, but you get the idea.
And that's basically it. Um
we we are using this quite heavily
internally as well to strengthen our
security posture. And with agents like
it's becoming more and more
uh relevant because it's easier for you
know, these vulnerabilities to be
discovered. So, it's it's more
imperative that we have the tools to
find them and fix them
sooner.
I hope you enjoyed this BCL session and
I hope to meet you in other sessions or
maybe in person if you ever come to a
conference.
Thank you.